{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This emperor’s attempts to permanently relocate to Alexandria led Cassius Chaerea to scheme against him. This man may have caused a famine when he relocated grain ships to form a pontoon bridge between Puteoli and Baiae. This man’s successor was found hiding behind a curtain after the Praetorian Guard stabbed this man thirty times. Claudius succeeded, for ten points, what Roman emperor who was accused of naming his favorite horse consul, among other insane acts?",
      "answer": [
        "Caligula",
        "Gaius Julius Caesar Augustus Germanicus"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was accused of staging a standardization demonstration by Merritt Smith in order to buy more time to fulfill a government order for 15,000 muskets. This man worked with Honore Blanc and Louis de Tousard to produce widely-used artillery pieces, an early concept of interchangeable parts. His most famous creation revolutionized the Southern economy by allowing for the easy removal of seeds from a certain cash crop. For ten points, name this inventor of the cotton gin.",
      "answer": "Eli Whitney"
    },
    {
      "question": "JME McTaggart formulated two possible conceptions of this concept, the A-series and B-series, in his work on the “Unreality” of this concept. Martin Heidegger’s magnum opus argued that this concept was “the horizon of being” and was titled for Being and this concept. Philosophical positions about this concept include presentism and eternalism. For ten points, name this philosophical concept which pertains to the past, present, and future.",
      "answer": [
        "time",
        "The Unreality of Time",
        "Being and Time"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man spent two weeks in the hospital before an event, causing Richard Daley to cry “they’ve embalmed him before he even died!” Dwight Eisenhower said “If you give me a week, I’ll think of one” contribution by this politician. This man’s 5 o’clock shadow and sickly frame hurt his performance in the first televised presidential debate against John F. Kennedy in 1960. For ten points, name this politician who recovered to win the 1968 and 1972 elections.",
      "answer": "Richard Nixon"
    },
    {
      "question": "Description acceptable. James Bradley notes that one participant of this event was shot by a sniper less than a month after this event; that man is Frank Sousley. Felix Wheldon used a depiction of this event for the Marine Corps War Memorial. Ira Hayes and Rene Gagnon were among the six people involved in this event, which Joe Rosenthal photographed at Mount Suribachi. For ten points, name this 1945 event in which the American colors were hoisted above a Japanese island.",
      "answer": [
        "the raising of the American flag on Iwo Jima",
        "equivalents that include all 3 parts",
        "acceptMountSuribachiinplaceof Iwo Jimabeforeit’smentioned",
        "promptonpartialanswers,including Battle of Iwo Jima"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This group was hurt by constant raids by the Victual Brothers against their signature cog ships. Though this group lost influence when the Steelyard was closed in England, they forced Valdemar IV to force the Treaty of Stralsund to gain greater trading rights in Denmark. This group was centered on Lubeck and formed by merchant guilds around North Germany. For ten points, name this Baltic merchant alliance active in the 14th century.",
      "answer": "Hanseatic League or Hansa"
    },
    {
      "question": "A group of these people were tried at Destrehan after trying to seize New Orleans during the German Coast rebellion. Mosby Sheppard convinced James Monroe to use the Virginia militia against a group of these people led by Gabriel Prosser. These people were prohibited from learning to read or write in many states after Nat Turner led a rebellion. For ten points, name this class of people who were the subject of the Emancipation Proclamation, which freed them.",
      "answer": "American slaves s"
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1929, Leonard Woolley’s team of archaeologists found four examples of this type of musical instrument in the ruins of Ur. A Samuel Barber Adagio for this type of instruments was JFK’s favorite piece of classical music and was widely broadcast after his assassination. Plectra, picks, or bows may be used to play, for ten points, what class of musical instruments that includes guitars and violins?",
      "answer": [
        "string instruments",
        "lyres and/or harps",
        "Adagio for Strings after “Samuel” is read"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This site was allegedly built in a single night to serve as housing for Ket Mealea. A new capital was established at the Bayon after this site was sacked by the Cham people. Completed by Jayavarman VII, this site was constructed to resemble India’s Mount Meru. This site was dedicated to Vishnu, but it was later converted into a Buddhist temple. A national flag depicts, for ten points, what Cambodian temple complex?",
      "answer": "Angkor Wat"
    },
    {
      "question": "This war included the controversial hanging of members of the St. Patrick’s Battalion for desertion. TheSpotResolutionswereAbrahamLincoln’sCongressionalattempttodiscoverthespotwhereAmerican troops were shot near the Nueces [nu-AY-sis] River in the leadup to this war. This war ended with the Treaty of Guadalupe Hidalgo, which gave California to the winners. For ten points, name this war in which the United States prevailed over its southern neighbor.",
      "answer": "Mexican-American War"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This battle began with light raids against shipping during the “storangriffe” period before culminating in a large scale strike on “Eagle Day.” Beta-carotene was used in propaganda as an explanation for why one side in this battle performed better at night. This battle led to the cancellation of the invasion plan Sealion and prompted the losing side to carry out the Blitz. For ten points, name this 1940 battle where the RAF thwarted the Luftwaffe over home airspace.",
        "answer": "Battle of Britain"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Carrots didn’t win the Battle of Britain; instead, the Chain Home system used this novel technology to detect incoming German planes.",
        "answer": "Early Warning radar"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This event was hosted by the subject’s daughter-in-law Jane because his wife was too sick to travel. The subject of this event was 68 years old at the time, a record later surpassed by Ronald Reagan. This event included a speech of over 8,000 words delivered by a man who wore no overcoat, despite cold winds and low temperatures. For ten points, name this March 4, 1841 event, essentially the only official action of the administration of the ninth US President before his death a month later.",
        "answer": "inauguration ceremony of William Henry Harrison"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Before his death, William Henry Harrison was able to make nominations for several Cabinet posts, including Thomas Ewing in this department. Other Secretaries in charge of this department included Roger Taney, Albert Gallatin, and Salmon Chase.",
        "answer": [
          "Treasury Department",
          "Secretary of the Treasury"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Mu’tazila school disagrees that this work is “uncreated” and thus co-eternal with God. This work, which was standardized around 650 AD by Uthman ibn Affan, was first shared in a cave where Jibreel ordered a certain person to “recite!” People who memorize the entirety of this text are called Hafiz. For ten points, name this scripture divided into 114 surahs and revealed to the prophet Muhammad, the holy book of Islam.",
        "answer": "The Qur’an or Koran"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The second and longest surah of the Quran is named for this animal. A golden statue of a young one of these animals was created by the Israelites while Moses was on Mount Sinai in Exodus, leading to their punishment.",
        "answer": "cow"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This battle’s victors followed up their success with an amphibious landing on Cavite. The McCulloch lost engineer Francis Randall to a heart attack in this battle. The flagship Olympia attacked after the signal “You may fire when you are ready, Gridley” was given at the start of this battle, in which only nine Americans were wounded. For ten points, name this decisive naval battle of the Spanish-American War in the Philippines.",
        "answer": "Battle of Manila Bay"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This admiral gave the command “You may fire when you are ready, Gridley” while leading the American fleet at Manila Bay.",
        "answer": "George Dewey"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This location was transferred to the Pitjantjatjara in exchange for a ninety-nine year lease. This location shares a national park with Mount Olga, which is part of the Kata Tjuta formations. This feature is notably never climbed by the Anangu, who believe that it is the site of a Dreamtime trail. In 1873, William Gosse named this feature in honor of Chief Secretary Henry Ayers. For ten points, name this sandstone formation sacred to Australian Aborigines.",
        "answer": [
          "Uluru",
          "Ayers Rock before “Ayers” is mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Uluru is found in the southwestern region of this Australian territory, whose capital city was bombed in 1942 by the Japanese.",
        "answer": "Northern Territory"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In a poem set during this war, a daughter of the nobleman Kochubei named Maria falls for the central character; that poem was inspired by a Lord Byron work about a figure in this war who served under John II Casimir. A story about the victor of this war describes a storm on the river Neva and sees Evgenii find the title statue of this war’s victor staring at him. For ten points, name this war described in poems like “The Bronze Horseman” and “Poltava,” a victory for Peter the Great.",
        "answer": "Great Northern War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "“The Bronze Horseman” and “Poltava” are poems by this Russian poet who was exiled by Alexander I and killed in an 1837 duel.",
        "answer": "Alexander Pushkin"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A kingdom once located on this island drove out Dutch foreigners in the Siege of Fort Zeelandia. This island, where the Kingdom of Tungning ruled, suffered a forty-year period of martial law called the White Terror. This island was ceded to Japan in 1895 per the Treaty of Shimonoseki, and Chiang Kai-shek fled to this island after his defeat in the Chinese Civil War. For ten points, name this island controlled by the Republic of China, whose capital is Taipei.",
        "answer": [
          "Taiwan",
          "Republic of China",
          "ROC before mentioned"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "After fleeing to Taiwan, Chiang Kai-shek continued the rule of this political party.",
        "answer": [
          "Kuomintang or KMT",
          "Nationalist Party of China"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This event led to the creation of a large chain floated on wooden logs in order to block entry into a harbor. The engineer Orban helped construct the large Basilica gun for use in this event, where defenses in the Golden Horn were breached. This event led the title of “Conqueror” to be conferred upon its victorious commander, a sultan who was just 21 years old. The Hagia Sophia became a mosque after, for ten points, what 1453 event that marked the end of the Byzantine Empire?",
        "answer": "1453 Siege or Fall, etc. of Constantinople"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Sultan of the Ottoman Empire became known as “the Conqueror” after sacking Constantinople.",
        "answer": "Mehmed II or Mehmed the Conqueror"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Women’s Suffrage",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Constitutional amendment that guaranteed women’s right to vote.",
          "answer": "19th Amendment to the US Constitution"
        },
        {
          "question": "US President who eventually oversaw the passage of that amendment in 1920.",
          "answer": "Woodrow Wilson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Suffragette who inspired the first attempt at an amendment in 1872, the same year she was arrested for voting in New York.",
          "answer": "Susan B. Anthony"
        },
        {
          "question": "Western state where women’s suffrage was removed by Congress as a punishment for the Mormon practice of polygamy.",
          "answer": "Utah"
        },
        {
          "question": "New York town where Lucretia Mott and Elizabeth Cady Stanton organized the first women’s rights convention in 1848.",
          "answer": "Seneca Falls Convention"
        },
        {
          "question": "Western state where women could vote in 1869 and which insisted on keeping women’s suffrage when it joined the Union in 1890.",
          "answer": "Wyoming"
        },
        {
          "question": "Suffragette and “Silent Sentinel” who led the National Woman’s Party for decades.",
          "answer": "Alice Paul"
        },
        {
          "question": "Suffragette who was elected to Congress in 1916 and who was criticized for voting against entering World Wars I and II.",
          "answer": "Jeannette Rankin"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "The Third Crusade",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Target city of the Third Crusade, which sought to reclaim it from the Ayyubids.",
          "answer": "Jerusalem"
        },
        {
          "question": "Reigning English King and successor of Henry II, who led the crusade with Philip II of France.",
          "answer": "Richard I or Richard the Lionheart"
        },
        {
          "question": "Catholic military order whose members fought in the Third Crusade, bearing distinctive white banners with red crosses.",
          "answer": "Knights Templar"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ayyubid Sultan who conquered the Holy Land in 1187 with unified Egyptian and Syrian forces.",
          "answer": "Saladin"
        },
        {
          "question": "Holy Roman Emperor who also led troops during the Third Crusade, but drowned in a river before reaching the Holy Land.",
          "answer": [
            "Frederick Barbarossa",
            "Frederick I"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "City in present-day Israel that was besieged by Guy of Lusignan in 1189 and eventually recaptured.",
          "answer": "Acre"
        },
        {
          "question": "Port city that crusading forces managed to capture in 1191; it also names the treaty signed to end the Third Crusade.",
          "answer": "Treaty of Jaffa or Yaffa"
        },
        {
          "question": "Crushing 1187 battle that allowed Muslim forces to re-capture most of the Crusader-held cities in the Holy Land, leading to the Third Crusade.",
          "answer": "Battle of the Horns of Hattin"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Apartheid",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "African country where white politicians created apartheid.",
          "answer": "South Africa"
        },
        {
          "question": "First black president of that country, being elected after years in prison fighting apartheid.",
          "answer": "Nelson Mandela"
        },
        {
          "question": "Trial in which that man was sentenced to life in prison in 1964.",
          "answer": "Rivonia Trial"
        },
        {
          "question": "Largest city in which apartheid was carried out; the aforementioned trial was named for a suburb of this city.",
          "answer": "Johannesburg"
        },
        {
          "question": "Language from which the word “apartheid” is derived; it and English were required to be taught in schools.",
          "answer": "Afrikaans"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sport played by the Springboks, whose 1981 Test tour of New Zealand was heavily protested.",
          "answer": "rugby union"
        },
        {
          "question": "Last apartheid-era President, a white politician who also ended his country’s nuclear weapons program.",
          "answer": "Frederik Willem de Klerk"
        },
        {
          "question": "1960 massacre in which 69 protesters against the pass laws were killed by police.",
          "answer": "Sharpeville Massacre"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This ruler briefly interrupted the Kingdom of the Two Sicilies with the creation of the Parthenopaen Republic. This ruler, who organized the Netherlands into the Batavian Republic, forced the Treaty of (20 pts)",
        "Campo Formio on his rivals. The Confederation of the Rhine was organized by this man as part of a network of client states imposing an economic blockade on (10 pts)",
        "England, the “Continental System.” After Russia refused to agree to this man’s trade policies, this man launched an 1812 invasion. For ten points, name this emperor of France."
      ],
      "answer": "Napoleon Bonaparte or Napoleon I"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) While searching in this body of water in 1935, Lorenzo Hagglund found the remains of a ship that is now displayed in the Smithsonian. The gundalow Spitfire sank in this body of water after the Battle of Valcour Island. (20 pts)",
        "Alexander Macomb was known as “the Hero” of a battle located on this body of water, where Thomas Pringle and Guy Carleton led a 1776 attack. (10 pts)",
        "Benedict Arnold stalled the British invasion of the Hudson River Valley by winning a naval battle on, for ten points, what lake, overlooked by Fort Ticonderoga, that straddles the border of Vermont and New York?"
      ],
      "answer": "Lake Champlain"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this war, peace negotiations were held on the USS Lackawanna. In this war, Miguel Grau led the ironclad Huascar to victory at the Battle of (20 pts)",
        "Iquique [ee-kee-kay]. This war began after one nation imposed a ten-cent tax on saltpeter, a replacement for guano that was mined from a disputed part of the (10 pts)",
        "Atacama Desert. Peru and Bolivia fought Chile in, for ten points, what 1879 to 1883 war named for a nearby ocean?"
      ],
      "answer": "War of the Pacific"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man attempted to become the first official to resign from the Soviet Politburo after Yegor Ligachev criticized him for allowing dissent as First Secretary. This man rose to fame by stopping the Gang of Eight’s coup with a speech given (20 pts)",
        "atop a tank. This man became the most prominent leader to sign the Belavezha Accords to establish a Commonwealth of Independent States, which formed after the (10 pts)",
        "fall of the Soviet Union. For ten points, name this first president of the Russian Federation and successor of Mikhail Gorbachev."
      ],
      "answer": "Boris Yeltsin"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man described his descent into alcoholism in his autobiography Magnificent Desolation. When invited for an interview supposedly for Japanese children, this man was accused on camera by Bart Sibrel of being a “coward and a liar,” so he (20 pts)",
        "punched him in the jaw. This man, who engaged in an over two-hour long spacewalk as part of Gemini 12, began another walk twenty minutes (10 pts)",
        "after the commander of the Eagle. For ten points, name this pilot of the Apollo 11 mission alongside commander Neil Armstrong."
      ],
      "answer": "Edwin Eugene “Buzz” Aldrin"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Roger Hilsman Jr. drafted a proposal to kill a leader of this country, which was authorized by Dean Rusk while the president was on vacation. Cable 243 targeted a ruler of this nation after that ruler alienated (20 pts)",
        "Buddhist monks in a series of pagoda raids. In 1963, this republic’s first leader, Ngo Dinh Diem [yiem], was assassinated with CIA aid. This nation, which was bounded by the 17th Parallel, fought the (10 pts)",
        "Viet Cong under Ho Chi Minh’s control. For ten points, name this American-backed republic that survived until Saigon fell in 1975."
      ],
      "answer": "South Vietnam"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was criticized in a political cartoon showing him pushing a black man down the throat of a reluctant abolitionist. This man, who once declared “I believe this government was made on the white basis,” argued that (20 pts)",
        "territories could choose to outlaw slavery in the Freeport Doctrine. This author of the (10 pts)",
        "Kansas-Nebraska Act lost the election of 1860 to a political rival he defeated for a Senate seat two years earlier. For ten points, name this politician who famously traveled across Illinois debating Abraham Lincoln."
      ],
      "answer": "Stephen Arnold Douglas"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This battle became necessary after the Vale of Tempe was proven to be avoidable by an approaching force. During this battle, warnings of arrows that could “block out the (20 pts)",
        "sun” prompted a general to reply, “we shall fight them in the shade.” This battle was won when Hydarnes led his troops through the (10 pts)",
        "“goat path” revealed by Ephialtes [eff-ee-all-teez]. The Athenian navy withdrew to Salamis after, for ten points, what 480 BC battle where Leonidas and 300 Spartans tried to hold off a larger Persian army?"
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Thermopylae"
    }
  ]
}